<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Memories on Dew Blog</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/memories/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Memories on Dew Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 11:00:18 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/memories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>The Mashgiach זצ״ל</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/post/the-mashgiach/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 11:00:18 +0300</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/the-mashgiach/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/post/the-mashgiach/flame.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Mashgiach זצ״ל" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the devastating news of the passing of the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל, the news that the משגיח, Rabbi Mordechai Zelig Schechter זצ״ל has passed just a few short weeks later, is a lost that brings to mind the the verse in Yishaiah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;על מה תכו עוד תוסיפו סרה כל ראש לחלי וכל לבב דוי&lt;br&gt;
Why do you seek further beatings, &lt;br&gt;
That you continue to offend? &lt;br&gt;
Every head is ailing, &lt;br&gt;
And every heart is sick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva, the one who sits at the head of the yeshiva, and the Mashgiach, the heart of the yeshiva, have been struck in such a short time. Oy! How far have we strayed to be stricken like this!?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the passing of the משגיח זצ״ל didn’t come as a total surprise. He had a prolonged two year battle with cancer ר״ל.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways it’s impossible to discuss the Mashgiach זצ״ל without also discussing his father זצ״ל . In many ways he was the embodiment of the teachings of Rav Hutner זצ״ל and his father. But the contrast of demeanor between the Mashgiach and his father could not have been more stark. The Rosh Yeshiva was someone who was to be approached with awe, and who the burden was on the talmid to &lt;em&gt;shtell tzu&lt;/em&gt;, to put in the effort to understand what he was saying. The Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל demanded to live up to &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; standards. The Mashgiach on the other hand, could speak to anyone on their level. He knew how to speak נגד רוחו של כל אדם, to the spirit of each person. To distill all the depth of the worlds of his father and Rav Hutner זצ״ל into something that we could relate to on whatever low level we were at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The humility of the Mashgiach was something to behold. He wouldn’t put on airs or make you feel small when talking to him. Every conversation I had with him left me feeling edified and like I had just gained insight. But also,I always had the feeling that the Mashgiach had enjoyed talking with me as much as I enjoyed talking to him. I don’t think I was just fooled by his kind demeanor. I think the Mashgiach genuinely loved his &lt;em&gt;talmidim&lt;/em&gt; that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My relationship with the Mashgiach started on the day he let me into the Yeshiva. He encouraged me to come to Chaim Berlin and had encouraged my learning and personal growth ever since. When I came to Chaim Berlin, in the middle of the zman, I thought if I got accepted I would be allowed to come next zman. The Mashgiach told me to go home, pack my bags, and come immediately. If he hadn’t done that, who knows if I would’ve ever made good on my commitment to go to Chaim Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Mashgiach was not only a source of support, he was also a source of inspiration. He was a poetic soul and a deep thinker who was always there to share his insights. When I was developing my own ideas and thoughts, he was always keen to discuss and refine them with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples of his poetic nature and his encouragement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He once told me that it was important that I realize what I was. That &amp;ldquo;you are a fresh breeze that came in blowing the dust off of these old seforim&amp;rdquo; (pointing to the Chaim Berlin library).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point he was sick in bed with the flu for a week. When he came back he came and sat next to me during first seder to share with me that, during the time he was in bed he was meditating on the מהר״ל (גור אריה) on the verse מקדש ה׳ כוננו ידיך - that something done with two hands is something you put your whole self into. “Hashem doesn’t ask us to subjugate ourselves to him to become lifeless, passionless, passive automatons. Hashem wants us to serve him with &lt;strong&gt;both hands&lt;/strong&gt;! With vigor and passion, full of life and power! Like knights on galloping horses, charging full speed towards the enemy full of strength and force of will!!” He then apologized for disturbing me during Seder on account of wanting to share that with me. (NOTE: I don’t remember what the גור אריה actually said, this is just my account of what the משגיח זצ״ל said)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed much of what the Mashgiach said was specific to circumstances, but planted a seed. In these cases, I was able to absorb the actual message immediately, but the underlying perspectives that went into what was said had a prolonged effect over time. I used to try to go to the Mashgiach’s home for סעודה שלישית. That was the time when he would generally wax philosophically. I’m certain that many of my life insights were formed from those times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When his brother in law passed suddenly, the Mashgiach took some of his young children to raise in his home. He would walk every Shabbos to boro park to make kiddush for his widow and give attention to his other children. I remember that once, when I was engaged to be married, I needed to discuss something with him. He suggested that we talk on his walk to Boro Park that Shabbos. I remember besides whatever I had to discuss with him, we also covered various topics, like Kabbalistic disagreements between the Chassidim and the Perushim and the philosophy of Radiziner Chassidus (his brother in law was a scion of the Radziner Rebbe). It was a truly uplifting experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comments about the משגיח זצ״ל are welcomed below:&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Rebbe Meir From Behind</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/post/rebbe-meir-from-behind/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/rebbe-meir-from-behind/</guid>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gemara relates that Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi said: The fact that I am more incisive than my colleagues is due to the fact that I saw Rabbi Meir from behind, i.e., I sat behind him when I was his student. Had I seen him from the front, I would be even more incisive, as it is written: “And your eyes shall see your teacher” (Isaiah 30:20). Seeing the face of one’s teacher increases one’s understanding and sharpens one’s mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.sefaria.org/Eruvin.13b.5&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Eruvin 13b - translation from Sefaria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the third post in a series of posts about my Rosh Yeshiva, Rabbi Aaron Schechter זצ״ל. Each one of these posts is written in tears. This post was going to be the fourth post. There was another post I had started writing called “The Angels Have Defeated The Sages”, about the suffering and challenges the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל overcame without ever compromising his learning and &lt;em&gt;avodas Hashem&lt;/em&gt;. However, writing about the Rosh Yeshiva’s &lt;em&gt;yissurim&lt;/em&gt; was too painful for me at this point; the pain of his passing is too fresh. I have therefore decided to write about some my impressions of the Torah of the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל, as the edicts of Hashem are straight, they gladden the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I usually preface what I’m writing with a disclaimer that these are just my personal memories and impressions of the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל, in this matter it would be silly for me to do so. I’m not so delusional as to believe that anyone would think that I, little Yankel Shore, came to understand even a drop out of the broad oceans that were the Torah, or even the approach &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; Torah, of a giant like the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל. Everyone is already aware that all they can hope to hear from me are nothing more than the table scraps that fell from the Royal banquet! As such I will just apologize for my brazenness to even have the gall to talk about this matter. I hope the reader will forgive me on account of my grief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-simple-reading-vs-the-reductionist-reading&#34;&gt;The Simple Reading vs. The Reductionist Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל would often emphasize the importance of understanding what the “pushite (simple / straightforward) pshat” was. But he would also emphasize that understanding the simple pshat, required making the effort to appreciate the proper context and the spirit in which something was said in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a simple example, in Parshas Balak, at the Shabbos table in Camp Morris, we learnt the following &lt;em&gt;passuk&lt;/em&gt; (Numbers 23:9).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I see them from the mountain tops, &lt;br&gt;
Gaze on them from the heights, &lt;br&gt;
There is a people that dwells apart, &lt;br&gt;
Not reckoned among the nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general context here is that Bilaam is hired by Balak to curse the children of Israel, but when he tries, Hashem turns his curses to blessings. The above phrase is part of his first attempt to curse the Jews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phrase “I see them from the mountain tops” is ambiguous both in English and in &lt;em&gt;Loshon&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Kodesh&lt;/em&gt;. It could mean either, I see those who are on the mountain top, or I, who am on the mountain top, see them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rashi, in explaining this &lt;em&gt;passuk&lt;/em&gt;, brings the Medrash Tanchuma that says that “the mountain tops” refers to the great Patriarchs and Matriarchs who laid the foundation of the children of Israel. This implies that it is the children of Israel that are on the mountain top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ramban, on the other hand, explains that Bilaam is referring to the fact that &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; is viewing them from a mountain top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Ramban points out, the fact that Bilaam is looking down on the Jews from a mountain top is not controversial. The last &lt;em&gt;passuk&lt;/em&gt; in the previous &lt;em&gt;Perek&lt;/em&gt; says so explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A student at the table asked the Rosh Yeshiva why Rashi, who usually explains things כפשוטו של מקרא, like the straightforward reading on the text, didn’t explain the &lt;em&gt;passuk&lt;/em&gt; like the Ramban’s interpretation, and then possibly add the Medrash as an alternative midrashic interpretation, as he does in many other places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva first gave a very straightforward answer - in Bilaam’s ”curses”, he’s not giving a weather report, he’s waxing poetically in praise of &lt;em&gt;klal Yisroel&lt;/em&gt;. In poetry, the &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt; meaning is not the same as the &lt;em&gt;literal&lt;/em&gt; meaning. Mentioning the fact that Balak brought Bilaam to a mountain top to &lt;em&gt;look down&lt;/em&gt; on the Jews is not really congruent with the gist of what Bilaam was saying. Especially the way our sages interpret the rest of the “curse” (as brought by Rashi).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva then decided that this was a teachable moment. For the next five minutes or so, the Rosh Yeshiva gave us a schmooze where he corrected various confusions and misconceptions about what “pushite pshat” means and what it doesn’t mean. I could never in a million years expect to do justice to the depth of insight and the clarity of thought the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל imparted to us in those 5 or so minutes. I will just relate one phrase that for some reason, echos in my mind. The Rosh Yeshiva said that some think it’s a form of sophistication to be very reductionist and try to reduce the pshat to be as close to the literal meaning of the words. “This is not a form of sophistication,” the Rosh Yeshiva said, “it is a form of &lt;strong&gt;blindness&lt;/strong&gt;!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-minds-eye&#34;&gt;The Mind’s Eye&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one summer, I had the opportunity to learn second seder with the Rosh Yeshiva זצ”ל in Camp Morris. We learnt Perek Arba Nedarim that Summer. Before seder, all sorts of people would come to make requests of the Rosh Yeshiva.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once, an &lt;em&gt;avreich&lt;/em&gt; came to get a &lt;em&gt;haskama&lt;/em&gt; on a book of diagrams he made for teaching children. I believe it was on the Tabernacle and the clothes of the Cohanim, but I don’t remember for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva looked at the sefer for a few moments, admired the artwork and accuracy of the diagrams. He then apologized to the author and said that he had no doubt he would get &lt;em&gt;haskomos&lt;/em&gt; from great Rabbonim, but that he could not give one. I don’t remember if the Rosh Yeshiva volunteered the reason, or gave it after being asked, but it came out that he was not keen on this kind of educational material in principle. He explained that a rebbe’s job is to help the &lt;em&gt;talmidim&lt;/em&gt; learn the &lt;em&gt;passuk&lt;/em&gt; or a &lt;em&gt;mishna&lt;/em&gt; and create an image in their mind’s eye from the source material and the &lt;em&gt;mefarshim&lt;/em&gt;. It’s not to show them a ready made picture that they can retrofit into the source material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunate are the eyes that merited to gaze upon the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל. Even if only from behind.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>The Reverence for your Teacher as the Reverence of Heaven</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/post/reverence-of-your-teacher-as-the-reverence-of-heaven/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/reverence-of-your-teacher-as-the-reverence-of-heaven/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/post/reverence-of-your-teacher-as-the-reverence-of-heaven/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Reverence for your Teacher as the Reverence of Heaven" /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rabbi Elazar ben Shammua said: let the honor of your student be as dear to you as your own, and the honor of your colleague as the reverence for your teacher, and the reverence for your teacher as the reverence of heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.sefaria.org.il/Pirkei_Avot.4.12?lang=bi&amp;amp;with=all&amp;amp;lang2=en&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;From Avos Chapter 4, Mishna 12 - Translation by Sefaria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second post in a series about my Rosh Yeshiva, Rav Aaron Schechter זצ״ל. I want to stress again, that I am neither qualified nor capable of writing a biography of the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל. The Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s memory should not be confined to the musings of Lilliputians like myself. I am just recording my memories and the life lessons I learned whilst being blessed to live in the presence of a giant such as the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rejoice-with-trembling&#34;&gt;Rejoice with Trembling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve got the impression from my previous post, that the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל was a warm and cuddly Zeide figure, I&amp;rsquo;m afraid I&amp;rsquo;ve misled you. The protocols of decorum towards one&amp;rsquo;s Rosh Yeshiva in Chaim Berlin were extreme, even for regular Yeshivas. I&amp;rsquo;m told this was put in place by the previous Rosh Yeshiva, Rav Yitzchak Hutner זצ״ל. The Rosh Yeshiva was revered and feared by all. And he didn&amp;rsquo;t suffer fools gladly. Even so, the love that he had for his students was felt by us at all times. He was known for having a smile that would light up the room. He was &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; known for the direct and no-holds-barred way he could express his disapproval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics of religion will often note the contradictory nature of the commandment to fear G-d, and the commandment to love G-d. Students of the Rosh Yeshiva have no problem appreciating how this is no contradiction at all. Because we felt the love of the Rosh Yeshiva, as well as his greatness of character, our love for him caused us to fear disappointing him even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unworthy-questions&#34;&gt;Unworthy Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never asked him, but I would imagine Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל was not a fan of the saying &amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s no such thing as a stupid question&amp;rdquo;. Firstly, the word stupid is not a word that ever left the lips of the Rosh Yeshiva. He would view such verbiage as coarse and unbecoming of a Torah Jew. But more to the point, the Rosh Yeshiva would lambaste students for asking (what we&amp;rsquo;ll call) &amp;lsquo;unworthy&amp;rsquo; questions, with some regularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A type of question the Rosh Yeshiva had particular contempt for was the lazy question. Where the questioner blurts out a question because he can&amp;rsquo;t be bothered to expend the necessary mental resources to come up with the apparent solution himself. The Rosh Yeshiva saw his role as facilitating a student&amp;rsquo;s deeper understanding and thoughts in Torah. He was not going to do the thinking for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a certain student whom the Rosh Yeshiva loved dearly and took under his wing, who he felt was guilty of this laziness to a certain degree. In trying to rid him of this habit, he would occassionally dismiss an &amp;ldquo;offending&amp;rdquo; question asked by this person with verbal carnage that made everyone else in the room uncomfortable. Once he even kicked this person out of the room for asking a question. He then told everyone else present, when he saw us all, mouths agape in horror, that he did so &amp;ldquo;because he is a good man, and I can be sure that when he comes back he will be a greater man.&amp;rdquo; (I&amp;rsquo;m not certain about the exact wording the Rosh Yeshiva used, but it was along those lines.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re worried about this person, it is true what the Rosh Yeshiva said about him. He did come back a greater man. I never received anything near that level of harsh treatment. The Rosh Yeshiva knew I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to handle it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;respect-for-all-students&#34;&gt;Respect for all Students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, one thing needs to be made clear. While the Rosh Yeshiva could be harsh in response to a question or a behavior, he would &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; treat the student himself with any form of disrespect. He would also demand that when referring to fellow &lt;em&gt;talmidim&lt;/em&gt;, or anyone for that matter, they were referred to with the proper respect. For example, he would take umbrage with someone referring to the &lt;em&gt;talmidim&lt;/em&gt; as &amp;ldquo;guys&amp;rdquo;. Someone telling the Rosh Yeshiva that &amp;ldquo;so-and-so is a good guy&amp;rdquo;, would get a lecture about how the word &amp;ldquo;guy&amp;rdquo; is a diminutive term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Parashas Bereishis, the Rosh Yeshiva would note regarding the verse (Genesis 2:15):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And HaShem took the Adam and placed him in the garden of Eden&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rashi, on this &lt;em&gt;passuk&lt;/em&gt;, quotes a Medrash explaining that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean He picked him up and placed him in the Garden, but rather that He convinced him with words to go to the garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How did חז״ל know this?&amp;rdquo;, the Rosh Yeshiva asked, &amp;ldquo;How does he know the meaning isn&amp;rsquo;t simply that He picked him up and placed Adam in the garden!? Isn&amp;rsquo;t that the simple reading of the &lt;em&gt;passuk?&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva answered, &amp;ldquo;No, the simple reading of the &lt;em&gt;passuk&lt;/em&gt; is like Rashi. The verb &amp;rsquo;to take&amp;rsquo; means different things in different contexts. A man is not a sack of potatoes that you pick of here and place there. When referring to men, &amp;rsquo;to take&amp;rsquo; means with words.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Rosh Yeshiva this was clear. Your fellow man was to be treated with dignity and respect becoming &amp;ldquo;the image of G-d&amp;rdquo; in which he was created. He was not a sack of potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;care-for-all-students&#34;&gt;Care for all Students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva cared for all the students in the Yeshiva deeply. Even more than they knew. I could probably write a book about this alone. I will suffice it to say that some students in the Yeshiva would possibly be considered &amp;ldquo;weak students&amp;rdquo; or worse by most accounts. When I got a little closer to the Rosh Yeshiva, he would often inquire about these students. I think, given my background, he felt I could relate to, and help, students who were struggling. On numerous occasions, he asked me to learn with a bochur who was struggling for a &lt;em&gt;zman&lt;/em&gt;, instead of with the study partner I had planned to study with. He explained to me that the Torah you learn while lifting the spirits of a fellow Jew is &lt;em&gt;Toras Chessed&lt;/em&gt;, the Torah of kindness. He understood that it can be very disheartening for someone not thriving in a Yeshiva. He did all in his power to maintain a connection with these students and set them on a good path in life, even if it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be within the walls of a yeshiva.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a certain young man in the Yeshiva who had a depressive temperament. On more than one occasion, the Rosh Yeshiva had me go check the dormitory to see if he was in bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you find him there, tell him I would like it very much if he would come over to talk to me,&amp;rdquo; the Rosh Yeshiva would say, &amp;ldquo;because he&amp;rsquo;s a good man and I enjoy speaking with him.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will always be grateful to the Rosh Yeshiva for this. Not only for his care, but for the way he encouraged me to care, and gave me an awareness of being נושא בעול חבירו, shouldering your brother&amp;rsquo;s burden. We revered him, but all the while, we felt his love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/reverence-of-your-teacher-as-the-reverence-of-heaven/ry-and-father.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;1856&#34;
	height=&#34;2400&#34;
	srcset=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/reverence-of-your-teacher-as-the-reverence-of-heaven/ry-and-father_hu431c93100e789e6e4aa04854938f95e2_144209_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, http://localhost:1313/post/reverence-of-your-teacher-as-the-reverence-of-heaven/ry-and-father_hu431c93100e789e6e4aa04854938f95e2_144209_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;The Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל with my father. (The current Rosh Yeshiva, Rabbi Shlomo Halouwa שליט״א in the background )&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;77&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;185px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>I Weep Over This Beauty That Will Be Buried in Earth</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/post/i-weep-over-this-beauty-that-will-be-buried-in-earth/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 08:57:12 +0300</pubDate>
        
        <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/i-weep-over-this-beauty-that-will-be-buried-in-earth/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/post/i-weep-over-this-beauty-that-will-be-buried-in-earth/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post I Weep Over This Beauty That Will Be Buried in Earth" /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gemara relates that Rabbi Elazar, another of Rabbi Yoḥanan’s students, fell ill. Rabbi Yoḥanan entered to visit him, and saw that he was lying in a dark room. Rabbi Yoḥanan exposed his arm, and light radiated from his flesh, filling the house. He saw that Rabbi Elazar was crying, and said to him: Why are you crying? Thinking that his crying was over the suffering that he endured throughout his life, Rabbi Yoḥanan attempted to comfort him: If you are weeping because you did not study as much Torah as you would have liked, we learned: One who brings a substantial sacrifice and one who brings a meager sacrifice have equal merit, as long as he directs his heart toward Heaven. If you are weeping because you lack sustenance and are unable to earn a livelihood, as Rabbi Elazar was, indeed, quite poor, not every person merits to eat off of two tables, one of wealth and one of Torah, so you need not bemoan the fact that you are not wealthy. If you are crying over children who have died, this is the bone of my tenth son, and suffering of that kind afflicts great people, and they are afflictions of love. Rabbi Elazar said to Rabbi Yoḥanan: I am not crying over my misfortune, but rather, over this beauty of yours that will decompose in the earth, as Rabbi Yoḥanan’s beauty caused him to consider human mortality. Rabbi Yoḥanan said to him: Over this, it is certainly appropriate to weep. Both cried over the fleeting nature of beauty in the world and death that eventually overcomes all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.sefaria.org.il/Berakhot.5b.14?lang=bi&amp;amp;with=all&amp;amp;lang2=en&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;From Talmud Bavli, Berahos 5b - Translation from Sefaria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://hamodia.com/2023/08/24/bde-harav-aharon-schechter-ztl-rosh-yeshivah-yeshivas-chaim-berlin/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;death of my Rosh Yeshiva&lt;/a&gt;, Rabbi Aaron Schechter זצ״ל came as a shock yesterday. He hadn&amp;rsquo;t been well for many years, and it was very hard to get in to see him. His memory was not what it used to be towards the end - I guess I had a lot of excuses for not staying in touch. The news of his passing hit me like a ton of bricks. It had been 8 years since I had last spoken with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I left the Yeshiva to study in Kollel Avodas HaLeviim (Ner Israel) in Baltimore, the Rosh Yeshiva told me &amp;ldquo;Yankel, you&amp;rsquo;re not leaving Chaim Berlin, you&amp;rsquo;re bringing Chaim Berlin to Baltimore!&amp;rdquo; At this time of great loss, I try to to console myself by telling myself that I didn&amp;rsquo;t leave the Rosh Yeshiva, I bring him with me every day. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to be so pretentious as to claim to be a &lt;em&gt;talmid&lt;/em&gt; of the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״ל, his &lt;em&gt;talmidim&lt;/em&gt; are great scholars and leaders of כלל ישראל. But when I was learning in Yeshiva Chaim Berlin, his presence demanded greatness from us! In consoling myself, I want to relate some personal stories I had with the Rosh Yeshiva זצ״לֹ that I take with me every day. This is the first of what will be a series of such stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-back-story&#34;&gt;The Back Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I came to Chaim Berlin, at age 22, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t your typical Chaim Berliner. Now, anyone who knows anything about Chaim Berlin will be rolling their eyes at this statement because to be a &amp;ldquo;typical&amp;rdquo; Chaim Berliner, you need to have gone to Chaim Berlin in preschool! So I guess what I mean to say is that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t a typical Yeshiva bochur at all. My Yeshiva high school education ended with my being kicked out of Mesivta of Boston in December of my 12th-grade year. From then on I wandered around, enrolling and dropping out of various Yeshivas and Universities. Eventually, I found work as a video editor. At this point, I considered myself to be &amp;ldquo;an agnostic&amp;rdquo; and found myself drifting away from religious observance altogether. A dangerous situation involving a car prompted me to make a commitment to return to Yeshiva and give G-d &amp;ldquo;another try&amp;rdquo; if I survived. When I did survive, I immediately regretted making such a commitment. Even so, I had made a deal, and I had to hold up my end of the bargain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first contacted Rabbi Eliezer Fireman, my 10th-grade rebbe, I asked him how I could get into Lakewood. When he heard the nature of the deal I had made, he told me that he didn&amp;rsquo;t think Lakewood was a good fit for me. He thought I would find it &amp;ldquo;stifling&amp;rdquo; and that Yeshivas Chaim Berlin would be a better fit. And so it was, that I called the Yeshiva to inquire about admissions, dusted off an old גמרא and prepared something to be tested on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-encounter-with-the-rosh-yeshiva&#34;&gt;My First Encounter With The Rosh Yeshiva&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most cases, you can&amp;rsquo;t get accepted to a Yeshiva, without meeting with, and getting approved by, the Rosh Yeshiva. I was the exception. The day I came to be tested the Rosh Yeshiva was moving and he couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it there to test me. As such, I was interviewed by his son, the Mashgiach of the yeshiva, Rabbi Mordechai Schechter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the first day of Yeshiva, I got up early, made myself tea, and started heading down towards the בית מדרש for שחרית. When I got to the lobby of the Yeshiva, I encountered the Rosh Yeshiva. The Rosh Yeshiva approached me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Good morning, who are you?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m Yaakov Shore, I&amp;rsquo;m a new student in the yeshiva&amp;rdquo;, I replied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yaakov, where did you find that tea?&amp;rdquo;, the Rosh Yeshiva inquired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva pointed to the tea in my hand. I found this question to be odd, but it was way earlier than I was used to being awake at that time and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be bothered to try to figure out what he was getting at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Downstairs&amp;rdquo;, I said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Then drink it downstairs&amp;rdquo;, the Rosh Yeshiva said with a smile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva was not keen on people standing around in the Yeshiva lobby, drinking coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-shabbos-table&#34;&gt;The Shabbos Table&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaim Berlin is a relatively big yeshiva. But because it is an &amp;ldquo;in-town&amp;rdquo; yeshiva, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer meals on Shabbos. An &amp;ldquo;in-town&amp;rdquo; yeshiva used to mean a yeshiva in New York, although I&amp;rsquo;m told now it increasingly means a yeshiva in Lakewood. Either way, I was from New England, which placed me squarely &amp;ldquo;out of town&amp;rdquo;. As such, I had to go to people&amp;rsquo;s houses for Shabbos meals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I soon found out that there were 8 spots for students to eat at the Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s house for Shabbos meals every week. I thought that would be interesting. In day-to-day yeshiva life, you don&amp;rsquo;t have much direct contact with the Rosh Yeshiva. I also assumed there would be a long waiting list, so I went to the person in charge of arranging the guests and quickly asked to be put on the list. When he asked me which meal, day or night, I wanted, I told him it didn&amp;rsquo;t matter, whichever was available first. He then clarified with me that was asking which meal I wanted to go to &lt;strong&gt;that Shabbos&lt;/strong&gt;. Can I go to both?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, I thought perhaps it was a fluke that there were spots available for that Shabbos. What I later discovered was that the Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s Shabbos table was not a typical Shabbos table experience. It would seem that most students preferred the normal Shabbos table experience. For one thing, the Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s wife, who had advanced-stage Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease, would be seated at her usual spot at the Shabbos table, this made some students uncomfortable. But I think the main reason bochurim didn&amp;rsquo;t like going to the Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s for meals was because there was &lt;strong&gt;absolutely no &amp;ldquo;shmoozing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; at the Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s table. For example, from what I can remember, the Friday night meal always went like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kiddish would be made. It would be followed by the Hamotzi. So far this is a normal Shabbos meal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s granddaughters would serve gefilte fish. So far still normal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the Rosh Yeshiva put down his fork, Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s granddaughter would clear the fish plates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s grandson in charge of the meals would bring out and distribute חומשים.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva would start learning that week&amp;rsquo;s Torah portion, with Rashi and Ramban, out loud. No talking, other than questions related to the material the Rosh Yeshiva was learning then, was allowed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At some point the Rosh Yeshiva would close his חומש and his granddaughter would bring out the chicken soup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the Rosh Yeshiva put down his spoon, Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s granddaughter would clear the soup bowl.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s grandson would bring out and distribute חומשים.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva would continue from exactly where he had left off in that week&amp;rsquo;s Torah portion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At some point the Rosh Yeshiva would close his חומש and his granddaughter would bring out the main course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the Rosh Yeshiva put down his fork, Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s granddaughter would clear the plates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva&amp;rsquo;s grandson would bring out and distribute חומשים.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Rosh Yeshiva would continue from exactly where he had left off in that week&amp;rsquo;s Torah portion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At some point the Rosh Yeshiva would close his חומש and his granddaughter would bring out the dessert.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe that dessert was followed immediately by &lt;em&gt;bentching&lt;/em&gt; and there was no study session after that, but I&amp;rsquo;m not certain about this last point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a joke they say about these long sessions of study at the Shabbos table when all talking was forbidden. They say that when a Chaim Berliner gets married, at this first Shabbos meal in his new home, with his new wife, he motions to her and whispers &amp;ldquo;Honey, could you please pass the salt?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I immediately saw the opportunity here to learn חומש from the Rosh Yeshiva. But sitting quietly all those hours definitely wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do. So I came up with a plan. Every Friday, I would study that week&amp;rsquo;s Torah portion thoroughly with every Rashi and Ramban. If I&amp;rsquo;m being honest, I usually only did the first half of the Parsha, or whatever I thought we&amp;rsquo;d get up to. I&amp;rsquo;d plan out a bunch of, what I thought to be, clever and open-ended questions on the material. Since everyone else there was generally silent most of the time, I figured it would be like having a private study session with the Rosh Yeshiva!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I quickly found out that I would have to up the ante regarding my prep work by a large margin, if I wanted to ask questions that the Rosh Yeshiva deemed worthy of responding to in more than just one sentence or less, the general plan worked great! The meals, of course, got a lot longer than they used to be, and not everyone appreciated that, but I paid them no mind. I told myself that if they wanted to, nothing was stopping them from participating, except maybe their lack of familiarity with the source material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back on this, I realize that was one of the ways the Rosh Yeshiva pushed us to grow. The Rosh Yeshiva knew full well what I was doing, but he knew that this was the driving force to me learning Chumash, Rashi, and Ramban every week. And learning them &lt;em&gt;well!&lt;/em&gt; I mean, who learns Chumash &lt;em&gt;well!?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One time, the Rosh Yeshiva smiled at me in the middle of a meal, put his hand on my hand, and said, &amp;ldquo;Yankel, I see you prepared שניים מקרא well this week.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I think about it, today is Friday. Perhaps, I&amp;rsquo;ll go prepare this week&amp;rsquo;s סדרה for the Rosh Yeshiva this Shabbos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/i-weep-over-this-beauty-that-will-be-buried-in-earth/rosh-yeshiva.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;2048&#34;
	height=&#34;1366&#34;
	srcset=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/i-weep-over-this-beauty-that-will-be-buried-in-earth/rosh-yeshiva_hu7706b00a5fbc1ae08205c2a3a1f029a9_178136_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, http://localhost:1313/post/i-weep-over-this-beauty-that-will-be-buried-in-earth/rosh-yeshiva_hu7706b00a5fbc1ae08205c2a3a1f029a9_178136_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Rosh Yeshiva and me at my wedding&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;149&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;359px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
